[Music]
hi everyone i'm anja parham pill and
this
is redlines my guest today is cia
whistleblower john kiriakou
who recently sought a pardon from the
trump administration
on charges he violated the intelligence
identities protection act kiriyaku is
the only
individual who ever served time for
charges related to the u.s
waterboarding program but that was for
revealing its existence
rather than participating in it john
welcome to redlines
thanks for having me anya let's get
right into it the new york times
recently reported that quote
a one-time top advisor to the trump
campaign was
paid fifty thousand dollars to help seek
a pardon for john kiriakou a former ca
officer convicted
of illegally disclosing classified
information
and mr kiriakou was separately told that
mr trump's
personal lawyer rudy giuliani would help
him secure a pardon for two million
dollars
kiriakou rejected the offer but an
associate fearing that mr giuliani was
illegally selling pardons alerted the
fbi
giuliani denies these characterizations
of course
but john is the times reporting here
true
uh i hate to say that it is true yes uh
all of it's true and you know to his
credit
mike uh schmidt the primary author of
that report
interviewed more than 30 people uh for
the article
it wasn't just you know john decided to
take a to take a cheap
shot at rudy giuliani uh he interviewed
a lot of people for that
article and so that means there were at
least
two trump allies attempting to sell
pardons just based on your story alone
yeah um yeah you know they made
a uh they made a differentiation between
selling pardons and lobbying for pardons
clearly this was pay for play uh
and boy you know where do you even start
with the story you know what anya i'll
start at the beginning
i have an attorney who has been
helping me try to get a pardon for many
years
he didn't really have very good contacts
in the trump administration i had
no contacts in the trump administration
and so we
decided to hire a woman by the name of
karen giorno
who ran the trump campaign in florida in
2016.
she is a uh you know she doesn't like to
call herself a lobbyist but she's a
political strategist for what that's
worth
and so we met with her at my attorney's
office here in washington
in 2018 and she told me that she was
very close to the president she showed
me the president's
personal cell phone number that she had
saved in her phone at least that's what
she said it was
she claimed that the president called
her uh in the middle of the night
on a regular basis to talk about policy
and politics and that she was still very
close to him
and for fifty thousand dollars she would
lobby the white house on my behalf
and if i got a pardon she would want
another
fifty thousand dollars uh i borrowed
the fifty thousand i didn't have it so i
borrowed it i gave it to her
and then essentially never heard from
her again and so
every four five six months i would call
and i'd say hey
i haven't heard from you in four or five
or six months what's up
and she would tell me the same story oh
uh
kellyanne conway is is on your side and
she's aware of your story
and sarah huckabee sanders is on your
side and aware of your story
and i talked to the white house
political director and he's uh
on your side it got to the point where i
said to her
one time i called her and i said so help
me god if you tell me one more time
that you spoke to the white house
political director i'm gonna flip out
because i don't even know who the white
house political director is but whoever
he is
he clearly does not have regular access
to the president
i said damn it karen i want you to go to
the president
and ask him to pardon me and if you
can't go to him i want you to go to
kushner
because she had been bragging about her
access to jared kushner well she didn't
know jared kushner
jared kushner wouldn't know her if she
had walked up to him on the street
and uh you know when push came to shove
she didn't help me get a pardon now i
knew that this was happening and i knew
that time was growing short
so last summer on the first of july
two business associates of mine and i
had a meeting with rudy giuliani and an
assistant of his
or an associate of his at the trump
hotel here in washington
this was to sell a very large number of
uh kn 95 masks to the pentagon
and so during a lull in the conversation
i said to rudy hey you know why don't we
talk about
uh a pardon and as soon as i said the
word pardon
he stood up and said i have to hit the
head
and he walked away to the bathroom his
associate said to me
rudy doesn't talk about pardons you want
to talk about a pardon you talk to me
but rudy's gonna want two million
dollars and i
i laughed at him i actually laughed at
his
face and i said two million dollars i
said listen first of all
i don't have two million dollars
secondly why
in the world would i spend two million
dollars
to recover a 700 000 pension i said
that's outrageous
and i ended the conversation now i
related this
to karen giorno and she told me oh well
you know that's the going rate i gave
you a deal
dinesh d'souza paid a million for his
and conrad black paid a million for his
and
she just went on and on well i related
this story later on
to a friend of mine another
whistleblower um
robert mclean the tsa whistleblower and
he said to me you know this sounds like
pardons are for sale and i said
that's a crude way of saying it but but
yeah i think that's really what
is going on here they they call it
lobbying
uh but it's not really lobbying i think
pardons are for sale
and even if donald trump isn't you know
getting the money at the end of the day
it's people like rudy giuliani enriching
themselves that's really what this comes
down to
even even if people don't have the
connections to actually follow through
as
as was the case with miss giorno yes
yes exactly exactly it was a money grab
is what it was whether it was karen
giorno or
any of the other you know dozen people
purporting to have had
close contacts with the white house or
close enough contacts with the white
house to
to get a pardon yeah that's what it was
it was a money grab
so i mentioned this to robert mclean he
was appalled to his credit
and um and he called the fbi and he
reported it
he reported it that rudy giuliani was
essentially selling pardons and the fbi
was not interested and robert was so
disappointed that the fbi didn't care
that this was happening that he called
the new york times and that's how they
got started on this story
and then as you say spoke with dozens
around 30 sources in order to cooperate
this this dealing regarding
the pardons john is is this kind of
corrupt
management of the pardon process unique
to the trump administration
no this happened during the clinton
administration as well although it
wasn't the lobbyists and
lawyers who were making the money it's
uh they were passing the money on in the
form of donations to the clinton
foundation
so this isn't specifically a partisan
thing it's not specifically a trump
thing
it's it just points to the corruption of
the entire system
and and let me add something about that
that i think is very important
the system that we have that allows
convicted felons to apply for pardons is
utterly broken
right the way it's supposed to work is
you go online
to the website of the office of the us
pardon attorney
and you fill out a form and you say i'm
rehabilitated i'm sorry for my crime
and i'm on the straight and narrow and
this is what i'm doing with my life and
then they turn all that
all of that over to the fbi the fbi does
a background investigation
and then when the fbi is done with their
investigation they
pass the file back to the pardon
attorney and the pardon attorney
determines
if yes you deserve a pardon or no you do
not deserve a pardon
so in a perfect world that's how it's
supposed to work the way it really works
is
ten thousand people apply for a pardon
every year and they recommend five or
six
people so you mean
out of 10 000 people only five or six
have really
rehabilitated themselves and so at the
end of the day
nobody gets a pardon well if nobody gets
a pardon
and if everybody knows that the that the
formal process
doesn't work then what are they going to
do well
if you're poor you're not going to do
anything because you're out of luck if
you have
money or you have friends in high
political places
then you go the lobbyist route and that
just shows you how
perverted this entire system has become
yeah how are you now advocating for
reform of the pardon system based on
your experience
well you know i've always maintained
that the that the
original authorizing legislation uh
back in you know the the early 19th
century
that authorized the creation of the
office of the us pardon attorney
meant or intended for the pardon
attorney to be independent of the
attorney general
we know that from contemporaneous
accounts
of the debate around the legislation
but it's never been independent it's
always been
seconded to the office of the attorney
general and that's just
wrong so instead of the pardon attorney
being housed
at doj it should be housed at the white
house
it should not report to the attorney
general
it should report to the executive office
of the president
and they should be able to make their
own um
determinations as to who deserves
forgiveness
and who doesn't deserve forgiveness
absent
uh political pressures because as things
stand now almost nobody
apparently deserves uh a pardon you know
at the very end of the obama
administration
uh obama fired the pardon attorney
for that very reason because the pardon
attorney would go years at a time
without recommending anybody for a
pardon
and that just defeats the whole purpose
of the office
absolutely while i've got you on the
line i wanted to ask you about some of
the intelligence priorities of the new
biden administration
on january 20th avril haynes became the
first biden pick to be approved by the
senate
she will serve as biden's director of
national intelligence
and we've been hearing a lot about her
role in the cia's drone program
as well as whitewashing u.s torture how
will she influence president biden yeah
that's a very
important question and a very important
issue avril haynes
is very very much in the mold of john
brennan
and gina haspel she was
she was brennan's deputy at the national
security council
she was brennan's deputy at the cia
and remember avril haynes who was
confirmed by the senate yesterday by a
vote of
82 to 10 which just
made my hair stand up um avril haynes
was the one
who was responsible for creating the
legal arguments
in support of john brennan's kill list
at the uh nsc it's avril who would take
you know the call from from the field
saying we have the
terrorists uh jeep in in our sights
request permission to launch
and she would give permission to launch
and invariably
we killed innocent uh civilians women
children
elderly and she never answered
questions at least not in my mind she
never answered questions related to her
role
in the drone program at least as
important as that
it was avril haynes who was john
brennan's deputy at the cia
when brennan ordered cia operatives to
hack
into the computer system of the senate
intelligence committee
the democratic staff because they were
writing the senate torture report and
brennan wanted to know
what they knew and so he ordered this
hack of the system well avril haynes was
in up to her neck in the hacking of the
system
so that's two little things i mean
little in terms of you know global
politics
that bother me another thing that
bothered me is we really don't know
where avril haines stands on
issues like china russia iran
counter-proliferation counter-terrorism
she never had to answer any of those
questions at least not in a public venue
yet she was she was approved by a vote
of 82-10
and is today the director of national
intelligence
for some reason many of these
picks or questions seem to have
bipartisan support
john what do you make of biden's
decision to nominate william
burns a career diplomat to lead the cia
now that i was very happy about i've
known bill burns
for the last 30 years
he has ably
served presidents of both parties
uh he was he was the point man for the
obama administration
during the negotiations with iran for
the jcpoa the iran nuclear deal
he devoted his professional career to
supporting human rights
and the arab-israeli peace process
he's the real deal and he is apolitical
to a fault there's not a political bone
in the man's body
he's had essentially every high level
position at the state department
from uh deputy secretary on down he was
ambassador to russia he was ambassador
to jordan
he was the special peace envoy so if
you're looking
for someone who's not afflicted with the
stink
of torture or guantanamo or
secret prisons uh around the world
uh he's your guy if if you're looking
for somebody
with the the political juice in the
bureaucracy
to actually reform the cia if that's
what you want to do
and i i think it's in dire need of
reform then bill burns is the guy to do
it
and it what was a mystery to me uh anya
is that um is that
joe biden could pick somebody as able as
bill burns
and somebody as disastrous as avril
haynes
in the same week i just don't understand
it
suggests a bit of schizophrenia within
the administration perhaps
some have said that the selection of
burns and you
alluded to this suggests that
negotiating with iran restarting talks
with iran will be a major priority
of the binan administration along with
friend of the show gareth porter you
actually wrote a book
the cia insider's guide to the iran
crisis
from your perspective why is the united
states so
fixated on branding iran as a top enemy
and how will the biden administration
approach the country yeah that's a great
question historically the problem that
we had
vis-a-vis iran was the specter of
communism
as quaint as that may sound now
the cia and the state department were
absolutely
obsessed with the notion that iran could
go communist
and of course you know in typical uh
american fashion we overreacted by
installing brutal dictators like the
shah of iran mohammed raza palabi
and his father reza palavi
in order to crush whatever left-wing
dissent there might be in the
in the country well of course they went
overboard as dictators are wanted to do
and they ended up oppressing their own
people and killing many
thousands of people that led to the
iranian revolution of
1978 and 79. um
we've never gotten over the iran hostage
crisis
like as a as a country as a government
we've just never gotten over it and we
don't trust the iranians because of it
well the iranians don't trust us because
of our interference in their country
spanning so many decades at the same
time
i know we always seem to need
an ism to to oppose
whether it's communism anarchism
socialism
as the decades roll by islamic
fundamentalism
it's like we we seek an ideology
to rally against because it helps us
politically
and i think that's that's the rut that
we've been in
with iran the the jcpoa the the
successful negotiation for the jcpoa
was a giant leap forward in american
diplomacy
the shame of it is twofold one that it
came so late in the obama administration
and two that it was not ratified as a
treaty by the us senate
so it could just be canceled uh by
donald trump as
it was well now joe biden wants to
uh reinvigorate uh reestablish the jcpoa
and the iranians are reluctant and i
think
deservedly so because their view
is that's fine you know we we
agree to go back into the jcpoa and then
what
what's to keep you from pulling out of
it again imposing crippling sanctions on
us again
you know don't forget these sanctions
these aren't just
paragraphs in the official gazette these
sanctions
have real impact people die because of
whether they can't get food or
medications or
fuel or spare parts people die
there's a squeeze and it's not just on
the government it's on the
citizenry and so the iranians just
simply don't trust us
especially now we're hearing that the
biden administration according to
secretary of state
nominee anthony blinken won't
necessarily return to negotiations
without asking for even more from iran
even though it was the united states
which broke the deal to begin with so
you know
tony blinkens another person that i've
known for a long time i actually took
his desk
when i went up to the senate foreign
relations committee
uh he he left the senate foreign
relations committee the week that i
arrived
and tony very much is a is a creature of
washington
he owes his entire career to joe biden
he has spent his entire career as an
aide to joe biden in different
capacities
he was a staff assistant at the senate
foreign relations committee and then
he worked his way up to be the staff
director of the senate foreign relations
committee when biden became
its chairman he followed biden to the
white house
uh 12 years ago and became the deputy
national security adviser then the vice
president's national security adviser
then deputy secretary of state uh and
he spent the four years working with
madeleine albright
and and other heavy hitters from the
democratic party's
diplomatic uh grouping of people and
uh now he finds himself secretary of
state
and he owes it all to joe biden
and finally john i just wanted to ask
you we know according to u.s defense
documents that since
early 2018 the u.s has placed a great
power competition
concerning russia and china at the
center of its
strategy why are our military and
intelligence agencies so focused on this
fight and how might it manifest
under biden and his cabinet this is a
dangerous uh policy development i think
instead of of engaging russia and china
instead of trying to
um to try to figure out where
for example in intelligence we can
cooperate with them for example
on counterterrorism counterproliferation
counter narcotics
we we challenge them and we just make a
a policy assumption that that we're on
the verge of a hot war
and so we have to prepare for that hot
war this is a policy
decision that was made many many years
ago
uh it's bipartisan in nature and
uh and we're in the minority in that
people like you and i want to see
cooperation and negotiations
uh but i don't think it matters really
who is in the white house i don't think
it matters
who the secretary of defense is who the
national security adviser is or who the
secretary of state is
we're going to be challenging russia and
china
uh in perpetuity that's
that's the lobbying that we see done
on the part of the defense contractors
that's the the uh
you know what else can you say
eisenhower warned us about the
the um the military-industrial complex
and he was exactly right
here we are now three generations later
and was we're still having the same
conversation nothing's going to change
and i don't care how
liberal people want to believe joe biden
is
uh our relations with russia and china
won't change
during blankens senate confirmation
hearings
a major theme was especially china and
even from
someone such as blink and who's not
considered as hawkish as some of the
other individuals
biden may have chosen for that position
then
the major threat blink and saw as well
as most of the senators on the foreign
relations committee was that
china is going to replace us as the
number one
power in the world and i think that will
just be a huge theme
throughout the biden presidency i agree
the chinese will replace us as the
largest
economy uh in the next 10 years uh but i
i agree with you tony blinken is a
neo-liberal just like
just like you know hillary clinton was
when she was the secretary of state
and don't forget that it was barack
obama who talked about the pivot
to asia uh turning away from russia as
our as our greatest threat
and uh and looking at the chinese as our
greatest threat that was a democratic
strategy
and i think that strategy is uh is still
in
in play uh during a biden administration
it certainly will be john kiriakou cia
whistleblower thanks so much
for your time you know we were really i
was really rooting for your pardon
and i'm sorry that about how it all
worked out but i appreciate you sharing
this story
and discussing some of the issues with
this system now just as you did after
your time in prison i know you
you talked a lot about the experience of
prisoners after after you started
to keep up the fight thank you so much
john
thank you anya take care
you